hi welcome back to alarm rim i'd like
you to show you one of my most important
students
one of my new students who's watching
the alarm room carefully this is joaquin
which is alias baby in phoenix right tim
and i'd like to thank i'd like to thank
hakeem and i'd also like to thank ale
for helping so much
especially with this retreat she's one
of
tim's main helpers in addition to
tatyana if i'm not mistaken
and uh pachi and pow and jordan and
thank god you guys and
so hakeem try to grow up fast because we
need you
all right okay it's okay let's go back
to
lamrim all right
i think we're at shepatar right
now
[Music]
sorry are we yeah no sorry one more
quotation
right tim jigley
by the way tim didn't know tibetan five
years ago
at all and now he's pretty good at it
so don't be lazy if you're like tim
you can learn to translate
super lay marking ink
they're trying to say that body cheddar
is like the most important thing and
there's a story
which is similar to the
myth of the big bang
there's another myth called the world
was created
when indra took mount meru
and churned the milk of the great outer
ocean and created the solid earth
from that in the way you make butter
from milk
okay so that's an ancient
myth similar to the big bang myth that
we
like okay they're all myth because
they're all mistaken
uh but you know they say god made this
world with
the they held a mountain in his hands
and turned the milk and it became butter
and that became the earth okay
why are they talking about that
they say bodhichitta is like the milk
okay and then you churn it and you make
the world
love makes the world go round okay how's
that
all right that's also from master
shantiduma
then he says in another sense
bodhichitta is like the butter that you
get from all other kinds of love
okay if you mix all kinds of love
and what do you call it churn it you
will get the
essence which is the butter okay ask
veronica about
butter when we go to a restaurant
we say hey can you give us some butter
and bread
anyway
then the llama makes an unusual comment
he says i beg you to
lose yourself in this river
i beg you to lose yourself
in this rumor i beg you to
forget yourself and become bodhichitta
okay it's beautiful the way he wears it
is very beautiful
all rivers flow to the sea you got a
picture for me you guys
you know all rivers flow to the sea all
right
jump into the bodhichitta river and you
will flow to the sea
okay it's a very beautiful thing
whether or not you are practicing the
greater way
depends on whether or not you have this
hope to jump worlds
from world to world and help people then
okay
word since you're here this is a tough
one okay i'm
not giving you the easy ones anymore
the relationship between being mahayana
and having bodhichitta is drunk
dog and it's not the drum dog you're
used to
yeah um
so the implication is if you have
bodhichitta draw
and if you don't have it don't okay
yeah you flunk you fail so the word is
very
delicate as my llama would say it's a
delicate worm
if you get bodhichitta you go
if you don't get it you stop so this is
a ghost stop
it's called in tibetan it's called a
ghost stop this is a ghost stop
body chitter is a gold
star why what's ghost dog mean
if you got it you go if you don't got it
you stop
okay you don't go anywhere it's a very
uh
kind of depressing word because the stop
seems to be more
frequent than the goal okay all right
cheers
forget subscribe for a while i
beg you take all those deep mantras
you know give it a break and i beg you
nen tensei
focus on bodhichitta for a while get
your buddy cheddar together
then go back to your donati how long
should i work on buddy today
okay two hours really
then go back to your dining but you know
go back and forth okay
because that's the gasoline for your
medicine buddha mantras and your vagina
guinea practice and your tarot practice
and your manjushri practice
and your amitabha practice you gotta
have
gasoline in the car okay keep filling up
the
body to the gasoline and then go
practice amitabha
or these other practices okay it's like
water in the desert
hey picture you got a picture for me
yeah
we live in a desert i mean we live in
arizona we live in a desert and
if you give water to a plant it goes
crazy
and if you don't water it it does like
gail says roses
somebody forgot the water in the how
long have they been there
10 years the roses were there for 10
years
some retreat and didn't know about water
and they killed them so don't
okay go stop it's like water in the
desert if the plant gets water
it's going to grow like crazy if it
doesn't it's
dead and it's sad i mean you should have
thrown out the
the the dead rose is kind of depressing
okay
[Music]
there's a lot of people here in tibet
they come from all kinds of traditions
sakya tradition
which is called the pale earth tradition
because their
main monastery is built on some pale
earth
sakya and there's gelupa
which is the tonkapa tradition and then
there's the kagyu
which is the i don't know um
early earlier than galupa galupa came
out of kagyu
and sakya and then ningma
which is the ancient ones the original
traditions of tibet
there's lots of people in all of our
traditions so pabunku
is talking look we're all the same we're
all
the same we're all we're different
flavors
of the same ice cream okay
and all of us in each of our traditions
we want to get to buddhahood that's what
we're trying to do
but then some people say look
i don't have time to learn about
bodhichitta
i don't have time to to learn abraham
about bodhisattvas
i'm practicing secret buddhism i'm into
tantra you know i'm doing mantras i'm
doing dharmanis
at sangya or dirk young chandragi send
me guppa
i'm practicing remy of tantra
what's that the two levels of tundra
what are they in brief number one
hooking up with enlightened beings
angels number one what's it called
kirim and then they teach you
how to change your body
the channels in the body and then you
become a buddha so those are called the
two levels of the secret teachings he
said everybody's talking about two
levels two levels two levels
nobody wants to talk about buddy china
they hope to cut some time off the
journey
they hope to speed up the journey okay
to enlightenment
hey there's a word there's an expression
for
that here in tibet there's an expression
for that
here in tibet and you have to understand
one thing about tibet
now the only cheap thing in the whole
country
the only easy thing to buy at the
grocery store
was salt okay they had big salt flats
you take a yak out there you load it up
you come back
you know you're in business
but there's something about some of the
much of the salt gives you a goiter it
gives you a tumor on your
neck a lot of tibetans had in the
old days they there's something wrong
with the salt and they would all get
these huge uh bumps on their necks
almost everybody in the whole country
had some bumps on their necks
from i guess it's from the salt or some
chemical in the soil okay
then he says you're one of those guys
wants to have a neck without the goiter
you know you're one of those guys wants
to have the neck
without the pump you know what's it mean
what do we say in in english
[Music]
yeah you want to have your kick it's
kind of like that
the implication is i'll show you i'll
show you a good example
look at this beautiful lady in the next
picture
okay this lady
i think that was last year surfing in
in san diego okay now suppose this
beautiful
lady came to geshe michael and said i
want to go surfing
but i don't want to get wet okay
i want to go surfing but i don't want to
get wet
that's i want a neck but i don't want a
glitter
okay i want quick
enlightenment but i don't have time for
alarm rim
or bodhichitta i'm going straight to the
dynasty you know
like i want to surf but i don't want to
get
wet yeah okay good luck
it don't happen that way okay right you
got to get wet
to go surfing you got to jump in the lum
rim if you want to do darkness
i didn't say that pabonka said that
okay all right i love that picture by
the way
by the way to be totally honest to the
whole universe
we are at the advanced stage of belly
boarding on our tummies
[Music]
and we gave up on the surfing okay but i
just want to
what do you call it when you tell the
truth in business full disclosure
okay
[Music]
but no buddha in the universe
ever got enlightened using medicine
buddha or anything else
without bodhichitta never happened never
will happen
you know he says
if somebody gets enlightened
with medicine buddha mantras or
vajrayani practice
or tara or amitabha without doing
lamrim buddy to the study that'll be the
first one in history
okay he's like that it's a joke you know
yeah
let's see if it works if it works we got
to put it in the museum
we got to put this person in the museum
because that'll be the first time ever
in billions of years that anyone ever
got to enlightenment
without studying lumberium without
studying buddhism
that'll be at first okay in english we
say
that'll be a first right all right
now okay word time for a commentary
now it's a difficult philosophical point
and i'm gonna see if you can do it after
five years
of working with you on mixed nuts by the
way the next
important book to be published
after the different kinds of karma book
it's gonna be words commentary on the
mind only school
the most difficult book of all
and he finished it and it's stunning
it's
really beautiful it's the best book
about mind only
i think ever translated on this planet
really
seriously and it's coming out soon from
the diamond cutter press
uh why am i talking about that because
the professor
smith is going to give us a commentary
on an important buddhist concept you
ready
well we're going to show the image while
you give the commentary you guys ready
all right here's the image you got it
can you see a word
that's good
all right now we want to come into it uh
in english in english we say uh every
dog has its day
uh something like that but sun came up
i i know but in tibetan it's like
uh the sun the sun even shines on a
dog's
dog's ass yeah not bad
okay into bed in the monastery
when you wanna say something happened
that never happened
before like someone got the buddhahood
using medicine but or any other mantra
without bodhichitta
then kikkum nagimasha then the next
thing that's going to happen is the
morning sun
will come up out of a dog's rear end
okay it means what
it ain't gonna happen okay it ain't
gonna happen i just wanted to
make sure your your buddhist education
was complete
okay and this is a very famous
joke in the monastery you know they say
i don't know
hey the cook finally made something
delicious in the monastery kitchen you
say
ah then tomorrow the sun's gonna come up
out of this dog's mirror
you know it means that i doubt it
[Music]
okay to get to buddhahood without
bodhichitta
it's like john brady sitting in the sun
in dominican republic right now
listening to me you're not going to get
a suntan
from a sun that came out of a dog's rear
end
it's not gonna happen okay got it it's
enough we
we we don't have to belabor the point
any further okay something that never
happened
before and which will never happen again
is happening to you if you can use
tantra
without bodhichitta without studying
bodhichitta okay
all right day cheers
if you don't want to study bodhichitta
you can forget
trying to become a buddha dila nen
please work hard on it please okay
that's the llama talking
rego attare jade
there was a famous or not very famous
uh tibetan llama called rego acharya
and he said to another llama named duke
kambana
ke omba na chandran
when you come over to my house
and we sit down for some tea together
you always bring the conversation to
love
you always start talking about love you
know bodhichitta you know
young then somehow i feel
uh my heart opens i feel when you come
to my house
among all my friends and you sit down
for tea
you always talking about loving or you
know love
and it just makes my heart open okay i
feel good when you come to my house
and i really don't feel like talking to
other people
you know people come over to my house
and gossip about politics and stuff and
and you come over and you start talking
about love and can you
visit more weapons can you visit more
often it's beautiful
okay
now he makes a comment
about our attitude about bodhichitta
oh geshla just spent a week
talking about doing my meditation so
good every day
that suddenly i experience
jumping from planet to planet and
meeting billions of living beings
and making a commitment to each one
personally geslat keeps talking about
this okay
aha that's
way past me you know give me some
mantras you know don't
i appreciate it it sounds nice
i believe maybe somebody could reach
that but hey i
it's too hard it's too far give me a
break
i'm just a normal human being it's too
much
i don't think i could do that you know i
have trouble
just sitting down once a day you know
i have trouble getting 15 minutes for
meditation you think i'm gonna
travel from planet to planet in 20
minutes
you know it's too it's too high give me
something more
more reasonable okay give me something i
can do
so that's one attitude on this side now
what are we going to have on this side
by the way in translation this is called
anticipate anticipate what he's going to
say next
no one guy says whoa too hot oh yeah
yeah
right that's come on that's easy stuff
i'm a tantric i'm studying tender i'm
doing
magic yeah i don't need this
normal old love stuff come on that's for
that's for movies that's for romantic
netflix movies i i that's too far
below me okay so some people are going
to say
oh geshla that's too high other people
are going to say kachi dei te chen tu
moi in
come on that's basic lamrim there is
sabarim nisso
i'm focusing on the two aspects of
tantra i'm a i'm a tantika i don't need
that number and stuff okay
gender nyamlan
means in reality the people who
really practicing bodhichitta are not so
many
some say it's too high geshella
some say i'm beyond that you know
but people in the middle trying to love
other people he says
you don't find so many okay all right
two extremes yay we got a picture
i've been using this picture for the two
extremes in emptiness
but it occurred to me you could use it
for the two extremes in bodhichitta okay
what's the two emptiness extremes i'm
gonna stop calling on word because the
bad habit
what's the two extremes as far as
emptiness
yeah yeah and then growing up to the
other side where you know
nothing matters if the husband yelling
at me in the kitchen
it's not my fault he doesn't exist
okay all right
got it either either
he's his fault one extreme
he had a bad day in traffic or he's
hungry right men
how to get men to be irritable don't
feed them
right either he's angry because he's
hungry
or he don't exist
i was studying emptiness i learned that
in the kitchen
if your husband yells at you you can
think he doesn't exist
okay yeah so those are the two extremes
now what's the two extremes in give me
the picture
what are the two extremes in bodhichitta
it's too hard yeah it's too high
i can't pluck my eye out and offer it to
somebody
what's the other extreme i don't mean i
am a tentacle
i'm doing mantras i'm doing donovan's i
don't need love
okay like that what's the ideal
middleweight
in this case
do your mantras do your mess in puna and
and love people okay that's all not very
hard
all right um how we doing on time
we still got some time
let's look at this picture
okay it took
no there's a better picture oh there it
is i'm sorry
you're right uh so in the main picture
you have the ocean
pacific ocean as seen from the sky scene
from a drone i guess
and i don't know it's difficult to see
the picture in the upper left
but that's uh a
bullock footprint a footprint of a cow
in the mud in india okay and if you've
ever been to india
you've met this like lots of times
okay so try to imagine
the amount of water you could put
in a bullock footprint
it's like half a cup or something right
try to imagine
that much dirty water
really dirty water and then close your
eyes and imagine the whole pacific ocean
okay this beautiful crystal
blue water billions of gallons okay
billions of gallons okay
then there's a where are jewels found
according to tibetans
in the bottom of the ocean okay you you
have to go
to the bottom of the sea to find a
sapphire
or a ruby or a diamond according to
ancient tradition all precious jewels
come from the bottom of the ocean and by
the way
the only way to mine one of the only
ways to mine
amber is to
sit on a mediterranean beach and wait
for it
because it's lighter it floats on water
it's lighter than water so uh
it when a storm comes in the
mediterranean
there are deposits of amber under on the
seabed
and they break off and they float into
the beach okay
like that's that that's the only way you
can get amber
but tibetans would that's probably where
the tradition came from
uh the only way to get sapphires rubies
emeralds is to go to the bottom of the
sea
what's the sea in this case
okay love for other people
as vast as an ocean i'm not talking one
planet
don't be these prejudiced people who say
i come from rimrock arizona
we support you know who for president
and he was nameless must not be spoken
we uh you know and they think rimrock
arizona is the whole universe you know
then they go to phoenix and you can tell
people from rimrock
in phoenix because the flies go in their
mouths
oh look a real grocery store
oh look what's that mall scottsdale
fashion mall
they go to scottsdale fashion mall they
walk down the mallet
okay don't come on don't be like a
remark
arizona person your planet is nothing
it's a little hole in the world okay
this
earth is a tiny come on
in the universe in history
it's a finger snap this whole planet
and all human history everything people
ever did on this planet
is nothing don't put your head
in a dirty little bowl
hoof puddle don't
keep your brain in a dirty muddy little
bull hoof puddle
take it to the pacific take your brain
to the pacific
because that's the only place you're
gonna find the jewels
got it okay that's what he's saying here
okay uh bodhichitta is the pacific
don't stick in your little local crap
okay try to think big okay go to the
pacific
that's where you find the jewels
imagine yourself jumping from planet to
planet
and put your mind there and i don't want
to hear you talk about
this world this is nothing okay
all right all right
therefore all the girl says
those those warriors
warrior gil says
they go to the ocean and they get the
real jewels
and they put it in the palm and they
make it their main practice got it
three minutes tim i'm watching i know
wait are we gonna do a okay
but we're not doing a lottery or
anything like that okay
[Music]
yeah well let's stop that's a good place
to stop actually